<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lantr.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://lantr.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-25T11:49:35+00:00</updated><id>https://lantr.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Lantr</title><subtitle>Lantr is a blockchain R&amp;D lab </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Blockchain Levels</title><link href="https://lantr.io/blog/2023/Blockchain-Levels/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blockchain Levels"/><published>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lantr.io/blog/2023/Blockchain-Levels</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lantr.io/blog/2023/Blockchain-Levels/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="level-0---bitcoin">Level 0 - Bitcoin</h2> <p>Bitcoin is the King.</p> <p>I buy the narrative. It’s the first one. Created by a noble and mysterious anonymous genius. Who disappeared and left the project to the community. Saint Satoshi Nakamoto.</p> <p>It’s energy converted to entropy and stored in a decentralized peer-to-peer network. The digital energy, the algorithmic scarcity, the digital gold. There will be only 21 million bitcoins, 21<sup>14</sup> satoshi ever.</p> <p>Many believe that, so be it.</p> <p>Bitcoin is reasonably simple, fairly stable. No hard forks since 2013 in Bitcoin Core.</p> <p>Bitcoin is unusable as a currency with 10 minutes blocks and 7 transactions per second. It’s a store of value, not a currency.</p> <p>Bitcoin is the Level 0. The Base Layer. The Sound Money in a world of Broken Money.</p> <h2 id="level-1">Level 1</h2> <p>We need to move money faster and cheaper. We need tokens. We need smart contracts.</p> <p>Blockchain of this level still needs to be decentralized, but it doesn’t have to be Proof-of-Work.</p> <p>All it needs is a secure, trustless and decentralized 2-way bridge to Bitcoin.</p> <p>These are my criteria for Level 1 blockchain:</p> <ul> <li>Proof-of-Stake</li> <li>Secure</li> <li>Decentralized</li> <li>Stable</li> <li>Fair distribution</li> <li>Smart Contracts</li> <li>Multi-asset</li> <li>Efficient Zero-Knowledge Proofs</li> <li>Fast</li> </ul> <p>I prefer Nakamoto Consensus over Byzantine Fault Tolerance as it’s more secure and decentralized.</p> <p>I see only two options here: Ethereum and Cardano.</p> <p>Everything else is lacking in one or more of these criterias.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/token-distribution.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/token-distribution.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>I think that Cardano is just a better technology than Ethereum.</p> <ul> <li>Cardano Ouroborous liquid Proof-of-Stake is better than Ethereum’s slashing Proof-of-Stake: <ul> <li>it’s more egalitarian as validators don’t have to be rich to participate</li> <li>stake is not locked and never at risk of being slashed</li> <li>peer-reviewed with a <a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2016/889.pdf">formal proof of security</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Cardano’s governance is better than Ethereum’s lack of governance</li> <li>Cardano never changed its monetary policy</li> <li>Cardano’s eUTxO model is a better than account model for zero-knowledge proofs</li> <li>Cardano transactions are deterministic, no wasted gas fees</li> <li>I believe that Cardano’s limited cap of Ada is better than Ethereum’s adaptive issuance model</li> <li>Cardano Native Assets are better than Ethereum ERC20 tokens</li> <li>there are further improvements in Cardano’s roadmap.</li> </ul> <p>Cardano is Level 1.</p> <p>Mutli-asset, eUTXO, predictable fees, deterministic transactions, smart contracts, zero-knowledge primitives, 20 seconds blocks.</p> <h2 id="level-2">Level 2</h2> <p>Fast BFT chains can become Level 2 sidechains of Level 1 blockchains. This is already happening with Cardano and Hydra, Cosmos and IBC, Polkadot and parachains.</p> <p>We can build a Lightning Network or <a href="https://ark-protocol.org/">Ark Protocol</a> on top of Cardano, and it will be more secure and decentralized than Bitcoin’s Lightning Network.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="bitcoin"/><category term="cardano"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Level 0 - Bitcoin]]></summary></entry></feed>